Harold H. Burton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Harold H. Burton Papers 1792-1965 (bulk 1935-1964)
MSS14472
Burton, Harold H. (Harold Hitz), 1888-1964
118,000 items
399 containers plus 4 oversize plus 1 classified
159.5 linear feet
5 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Associate justice of the United States Supreme Court and United States senator. Diaries, correspondence, legal case files, speeches and writings, reports, photographs, maps, printed matter, and newspaper clippings pertaining primarily to Burton's activities as an associate justice of the Supreme Court and Senator.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Brennan, William J., 1906-1997--Correspondence.; Brewster, Owen, 1888-1961--Correspondence.; Bricker, John W. (John William), 1893-1986--Correspondence.; Bridges, Styles, 1898-1961--Correspondence.; Brown, Oliver, 1918-1961--Trials, litigation, etc.; Burton, Harold H. (Harold Hitz), 1888-1964.; Byrd, Harry F. (Harry Flood), 1887-1966--Correspondence.; Clark, Tom C. (Tom Campbell), 1899-1977--Correspondence.; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980--Correspondence.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence.; Harlan, John M. (John Marshall), 1899-1971--Correspondence.; Hart, Earl E.--Correspondence.; Hitz family.; Hitz, William, 1872-1935--Correspondence.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972--Correspondence.; Jackson, Robert H., 1892-1954--Correspondence.; Lausche, Frank John, 1895-1990--Correspondence.; Minton, Sherman, 1890-1965--Correspondence.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949--Correspondence.; Reed, Stanley Forman, 1884-1980--Correspondence.; Richberg, Donald R. (Donald Randall), 1881-1960--Correspondence.; Sawyer, Charles, 1887-1979--Trials, litigation, etc.; Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946--Correspondence.; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953--Correspondence.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972--Correspondence.; Vinson, Fred M., 1890-1953--Correspondence.; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965--Correspondence.; Whittaker, Charles Evans, 1901-1973--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Association of the Red Cross.; American Legion.; American Unitarian Association.; Bowdoin College.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Standard Oil Company--Trials, litigation, etc.; Topeka (Kan.). Board of Education--Trials, litigation, etc.; Townsend Plan, Inc.; United Nations.; United States. Congress. Senate.; United States. Congress. Senate. Special Committee Investigating the National Defense Program.; United States. Court of Appeals (District of Columbia Circuit); United States. Federal Trade Commission--Trials, litigation, etc.; United States. Office of Price Administration.; United States. Supreme Court.; Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company--Trials, litigation, etc.
Subjects
Constitutional law--United States.; Law--United States.; Petroleum law and legislation--United States--Cases.; Practice of law--Ohio--Cleveland.; Segregation in education--Law and legislation--United States.; Steel industry and trade--Law and legislation--United States.
Places
Alaska.; Cleveland (Ohio)--Politics and government.; Ohio--Politics and government--1865-1950.; Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.
Occupations
Judges.; Justices, U.S. Supreme Court.; Lawyers.; Mayors--Ohio--Cleveland.; Senators, U.S. Congress--Ohio.
Provenance
The papers of Harold H. Burton, mayor of Cleveland, Ohio, United States senator, and associate justice of the United States Supreme Court, were given by Justice Burton to the Library of Congress between 1959 and 1963. Additional material was given in 1965 by his son, William S. Burton.
Transfers
Most photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Harold H. Burton are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified items in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified material.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on five reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1888, June 22 Born, Jamaica Plain, Mass.
1905 Graduated from Newton High School, Newton, Mass.
1909 A.B., Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine
1912 LL.B., Harvard University Law School, Cambridge, Mass. Married Selma Florence Smith
1912 1914 Practiced law with the firm of Gage, Wilber and Wachner, Cleveland, Ohio
1914 1916 Assistant attorney, Utah Power and Light Co. and the Utah Light and Traction Co., Salt Lake City, Utah
1916 1917 Attorney, Idaho Power Co. and the Boise Valley Traction Co., Boise, Idaho
1917 1919 First lieutenant and captain, 361st Regiment, Ninety-first Division, United States Army, American Expeditionary Forces
1919 1925 Practiced law with and later a member of the firm of Day, Day, and Wilkins, Cleveland, Ohio
1921 Published 600 Days' Service: A History of the 361st Infantry Regiment of the United States Army (Portland, Oreg.: James, Kerns, and Abbott Co. 276 pp.)
1921 1922 Major, Cleveland Grays, Cleveland, Ohio
1923 1925 Instructor, corporation law, Western Reserve University Law School, Cleveland, Ohio
1925 1929 Member, Cull, Burton, and Laughlin law firm, Cleveland, Ohio
1926 1927 Chairman, Cuyahoga County Council of the American Legion
1926 1928 President, First Unitarian Church, Cleveland, Ohio
1928 1929 Member, Board of Education, East Cleveland, Ohio
1929 Member, Ohio House of Representatives, 88th General Assembly
1929 1932 Director of law, Cleveland, Ohio
1930 Acting city manager, Cleveland, Ohio
1931 1932 Acting mayor, Cleveland, Ohio
1932 1933 Chairman, Inter-City Committee of Lake Erie Ports
1932 1936 Member, Andrews, Hadden, and Burton law firm, Cleveland, Ohio
1934 1935 Chairman, County Charter Commission, Cuyahoga County, Ohio
1935 1940 Mayor, Cleveland, Ohio
1937 1940 Member, Board of Trustees of the United States Conference of Mayors
1937 1946 Member, Board of Incorporators of the American Red Cross
1941 1945 United States Senator from Ohio
1944 1946 National moderator, American Unitarian Association
1945 1958 Associate justice, Supreme Court of the United States
1964, Oct. 28 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Harold Hitz Burton (1888-1964) span the years 1792 to 1965, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1935 to 1964. The collection includes diaries, correspondence, reports, legal case files, speeches and writings, newspaper clippings, and printed matter relating chiefly to Burton's service as associate justice of the Supreme Court and United States senator from Ohio. The material is organized in the following series: Diaries, General Correspondence, Senate File, Supreme Court File, United States Court of Appeals File, Speeches and Writings File, Miscellany, Classified, and Oversize.
Burton's diaries begin in 1941 and continue through 1963 covering his service as senator and associate justice. They are a rich and comprehensive record of his personal activities, the work of the Supreme Court, and conversations with members of the Court and numerous other government figures.
The General Correspondence briefly treats Burton's life and career in Cleveland, Ohio, prior to his election to the United States Senate. During this period he practiced law, was active in community activities, and served in various city government offices climaxing in his election as mayor. Notable topics in the correspondence are community affairs, family matters, Burton's association with local and statewide Republican party affairs, aspirations for a federal judgeship, and the Townsend Plan. Correspondents include Owen Brewster, John W. Bricker, Burton's personal secretary Earl E. Hart, William Hitz, and Robert A. Taft. This period of Burton's career is documented additionally by political speeches and radio broadcasts in the Speeches and Writings File.
The Senate File represents Burton's one term in the United States Senate where he established himself as a moderate Republican. He served on several Senate committees, including the Special Committee Investigating the National Defense Program which brought him into close contact with its chairman, Harry S. Truman. Burton later would become President Truman's first appointee to the Supreme Court. The Committees file documents his work on this committee and his extensive travels to Alaska, the West Coast, and the Middle East. Other committees represented in the file include Immigration, District of Columbia, Commerce, and Appropriations. The correspondence for the Senate years is grouped into four types: campaign, departments and agencies, general, and legislative. The campaign correspondence relates to party workers and organizations throughout Ohio during his Senate election in 1940. Correspondence with government departments and agencies includes appeals for constituents, especially for those in military service. Burton's legislative interests included hospital construction, foreign relations, and establishment of the United Nations. Noteworthy in the general correspondence are copies of Burton's semiannual constituent reports and accompanying responses. Correspondents include Styles Bridges, Harry Flood Byrd (1887-1966), Frank J. Lausche, Donald R. Richberg, Harry S. Truman, and Henry Agard Wallace.
The Supreme Court File documents the judicial activities of Burton and his fellow justices from 1945 to 1958. Material covering this aspect of his career is organized by correspondence, a case file, and a miscellany file. Among the legal material and correspondence are letters, notes, and memoranda from the various members of the Court, most frequently Felix Frankfurter. Others justices represented, some in the correspondence file and others in notes and memoranda retained in the legal files, are chief justices Harlan F. Stone, Fred M. Vinson, and Earl Warren and associate justices William J. Brennan, Tom C. Clark, William O. Douglas, John M. Harlan, Robert H. Jackson, Sherman Minton, Frank Murphy, Stanley F. Reed, and Charles E. Whittaker. Other correspondents include Owen Brewster, John W. Bricker, J. Edgar Hoover, and Harry S. Truman.
The Supreme Court case file contains conference lists, docket sheets with conference votes and brief notes on the justices' positions, bench and certiorari memoranda prepared by Burton's law clerks for study and recommendation, opinions, and studies on individual cases. Though not a prolific opinion writer, Burton saved most of the drafts of the various stages of his opinions along with comments in memoranda or actual annotations by his colleagues on the Court on their copies of opinions which they returned to him. Burton generally retained files on an average of ten to fifteen cases per term, usually the ones in which he wrote a majority, dissenting, or concurring opinion. His specific fields of interest, and the areas in which he was frequently assigned to write the majority opinions, were labor law and state claims versus federal claims. Included in his case files is material related to such landmark cases as Standard Oil v. Federal Trade Commission (October term 1949), for which he wrote the majority opinion, the steel company case Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company v. Sawyer (October term 1952), for which he wrote a concurring opinion, and Brown v. Board of Education (October Term 1953), in which the Court's unanimous opinion was expressed by Chief Justice Earl Warren. A miscellany file in the Supreme Court File includes bound copies of Burton's opinions and official statements from the bench, miscellaneous notes and memoranda from other justices, handwritten notes on Supreme Court history and its previous decisions, Court budgets and statistics, material pertaining to rules for federal courts, hearing lists, case assignments, and moot court competitions.
Upon retiring from the Court in 1958, Burton frequently sat on the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit, where he was active until his health failed in 1962. The United States Court of Appeals File documents the cases in which he wrote opinions for this court as well as other cases in which he participated. The opinions are similar to those for the individual cases on the Supreme Court, although less in number and in detail.
The Speeches and Writings File covers all periods of Burton's career and contains handwritten and typed drafts and printed copies of his articles, speeches, and statements. A group of articles relates to the Supreme Court and its history, and political speeches document Burton's tenure as mayor of Cleveland. Although the subject file in the series contains speeches and articles as well as pertinent research material covering his years in Cleveland, the Senate, and the Court, a chronological file contains the most comprehensive compilation of Burton's speeches and writings.
The Miscellany series is composed primarily of newspaper clippings and printed matter related to Burton's career and interests. A set of unbound scrapbooks of autographed material includes letters from Harry S. Truman and members of the Supreme Court. Also included is biographical material and genealogical information on the Hitz family. Oversize material includes maps pertaining to Burton's trips with the Senate Special Committee Investigating the National Defense Program, broadsides, and photographs.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in nine series:
Diaries, 1941-1963
General Correspondence, 1924-1940
Senate File, 1926-1947
Supreme Court File, 1792-1965
United States Court of Appeals File, 1958-1962
Speeches and Writings File, 1878-1962
Miscellany, 1896-1964
Classified, 1942-1943
Oversize, 1927-1952
Container List
- Diaries, 1941-1963 (Box 1-5)
  Bound volumes.
  Arranged chronologically.
  Available on microfilm. Microfilm shelf no. 17,858
  - 1941-1944 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1945-1948, (2 folders) (Reel 2)
  - 1949-1953, (3 folders) (Box 2, Reel 3)
  - 1954-1957, (2 folders) (Box 3, Reel 4)
  - 1958-1961, (2 folders) (Box 4, Reel 5)
  - 1962-1963 (Box 5)
- General Correspondence, 1924-1940 (Box 6-13)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization or by topic and chronologically or alphabetically therein.
  - Adamic, Louis, 1938-1940 (Box 6)
  - American Red Cross, 1939-1940
  - American Security and Trust Co., Washington, D.C., 1939-1940
  - Associations and clubs, 1939-1940
  - Autographs, requests, 1940
  - “A” miscellaneous, 1939-1940
  - Birthday greetings, 1940
  - Brewster, Owen, 1940
  - Bricker, John W., 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Burton, Deborah, 1939-1940
  - Burton, Felix Arnold, 1932-1940, (4 folders)
  - Burton, Robert S., 1939-1940
  - Burton, Ross, 1938-1940, undated
  - Burton, William S., 1939-1940
  - Business announcements, 1940
  - “B” miscellaneous, 1937-1940, undated, (3 folders)
  - Charitable donations, requests, 1940, undated
  - Cleveland Community Fund, Cleveland, Ohio, 1940
  - Colby Junior College, New London, N.H., 1939-1940
  - Condolences, 1939-1940, undated (Box 8)
  - “C” miscellaneous, 1937-1940, (4 folders)
  - Death and funeral notices, 1940
  - “D” miscellaneous, 1938-1940
  - Employment inquiries, 1940, (4 folders)
  - “E” miscellaneous, 1938-1940
  - Farm problems, 1940
  - Federal judgeship, consideration for, 1928, (4 folders)
  - Fenn College, Cleveland, Ohio, 1939-1940 (Box 9)
  - Flor, Grace A., 1936-1940
  - Freemasons, 1936-1940
  - “F” miscellaneous, 1935-1940
  - Gregory, Eleanor G., 1935-1939
  - “G” miscellaneous, 1938-1940
  - Hart, Earl E., 1937-1940
  - Hatch Political Activities Act, 1936-1940
  - Hitz, Frederick, 1934-1940
  - Hitz, Henry B., 1939-1940
  - Hitz, William, 1924-1935, (4 folders)
  - “H-K” miscellaneous, 1937-1940, (5 folders) (Box 10)
  - Labor unions, 1940
  - Letters of introduction, 1935-1940, (4 folders)
  - “L” miscellaneous, 1930-1940
  - Mayoral inaugurations, 1935-1939
  - Medicine and politics, 1940
  - Memberships, 1939-1940
  - Military Order of the Purple Heart, Cleveland, Ohio, 1936-1939
  - “M” miscellaneous, 1937-1940, undated, (2 folders)
  - Ninety-First Division Association, 1936-1939, undated
  - “N” miscellaneous, 1936-1940 (Box 11)
  - Oberlin College, Oberlin, Ohio, 1940
  - “O” miscellaneous, 1938-1940, undated
  - Photographs, requests for, 1940, undated
  - Political lists, 1940, (2 folders)
  - “P” miscellaneous, 1939-1940
  - Recommendations
    - Miscellaneous, 1936-1940, (5 folders)
    - State government, 1938-1939
  - Republican party
    - Clubs, Cuyahoga County, Ohio, 1940
    - Republican Central Committee and Republican Executive Committee, Cuyahoga County, Ohio, 1936-1940 (Box 12)
    - Republican National Committee, 1940
    - Republican State Central and Executive Committee, Columbus, Ohio, 1940
    - State convention, Columbus, Ohio, 1938
    - Ward clubs, Ohio, 1935-1940
  - Reserve officers, United States Army, 1940
  - “R” miscellaneous, 1938-1940
  - Saffold, J. Webb, 1939-1940
  - “S” miscellaneous, 1934-1940, (2 folders)
  - Taft, Robert A. (1889-1953), 1939-1940
  - Thank-you letters, 1940
  - Townsend Plan, Inc.,1940
  - “T” miscellaneous, 1936-1940
  - Uhrig, Ann I., 1940
  - “U” miscellaneous, 1937-1940
  - Veterans' organizations, 1939-1940
  - “V” miscellaneous, 1936-1940
  - “W” miscellaneous, 1937-1940 (Box 13)
  - YMCA of Cleveland, Ohio, 1939-1940
  - “Y-Z” miscellaneous, 1938-1940
- Senate File, 1926-1947 (Box 13-55)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1945 (Box 13-49)
    Grouped in campaign, departments and agencies, general, and legislative catagories. Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization or by topic and chronologically or alphabetically therein.
    - Campaign (Box 13)
      - Ohio counties
        - Ad-Ca, 1939-1940, (20 folders)
        - Ch-Fai, 1938-1940, (25 folders) (Box 14)
        - Fay-Gu, 1940, (22 folders) (Box 15)
        - Ha-Ja, 1940, (24 folders) (Box 16)
        - Je-Lo, 1939-1940, (17 folders) (Box 17)
        - Lu-Monr, 1939-1940, (21 folders) (Box 18)
        - Mont-Ro, 1939-1940, (32 folders) (Box 19)
        - Sa-Su, 1939-1940, (18 folders) (Box 20)
        - Tr-Wy, 1939-1940, (22 folders) (Box 21)
      - University and College Graduates Division
    - Departments and agencies
      - Agriculture Department, 1945
      - Civil Service Commission, 1945
      - Commerce Department, 1945
      - Employees Compensation Committee, 1942
      - Executive Office of the President
        - Foreign Economic Administration
          - Miscellany, 1944-1945
          - Sugar shipment to Spain, 1945
        - Miscellany, 1945
        - Office of Defense Transportation, 1945 (Box 22)
        - Office of Economic Stabilization, 1945
        - Office of Price Administration
          - Automobile repairs, 1945
          - Barbers and beauticians, 1945
          - Bread, 1944-1945
          - Kaye, Gabriel S., 1945
          - Leather, 1945
          - Meat, 1945
          - Miscellany, 1945, (6 folders)
          - Price charts, 1945
          - Regional offices, 1944-1945
        - Office of War Information, 1945
        - Office of War Mobilization and Reconversion, 1945
        - Surplus Property Board, 1944-1945
        - War Committee on Conventions, 1945
        - War Food Administration (Box 23)
          - Bakeries, 1945
          - Brewers, 1945
          - Miscellany, 1945
        - War Manpower Commission, 1945
        - War Production Board
          - American Crayon Co., 1945
          - Glass, packaging of, 1945
          - Miscellany
            - Individuals, 1944-1945
            - Industries, 1944-1945, undated, (2 folders)
          - Textile Order M-388, 1945, (3 folders)
      - Federal Communications Commission, radio frequencies and medical services, 1945, (2 folders)
      - Federal Power Commission, 1945 (Box 24)
      - Federal Reserve System, 1945
      - Federal Security Agency
        - Miscellany, 1944-1945
        - Social Security Board, 1945
      - Federal Works Agency, 1945
      - General Accounting Office, 1944-1945
      - Interior Department
        - Fish and Wildlife Service, 1945
        - Miscellany, 1945
      - Justice Department
        - Immigration and Naturalization Service, 1944-1945
        - Miscellany, 1945
      - Labor Department, 1945
      - Library of Congress
        - Journal of the Parliaments of the Empire, 1945
        - Miscellany, 1945
      - National Housing Agency
        - Federal Housing Administration, 1945
        - Federal Public Housing Authority, 1943-1945
        - Miscellany, 1945
      - Navy Department
        - Cleveland (light cruiser), 1941-1942, (2 folders)
        - Coast Guard, 1944-1945
        - Marine Corps, 1945
        - Miscellany, 1945
        - Personnel, 1945
          - A-G
          - H-Z, (2 folders) (Box 25)
      - Post Office Department, 1945
      - Reconstruction Finance Corp., 1945
      - Selective Service System, 1945
      - State Department
        - Italy, 1945
        - Miscellany, 1945, (2 folders)
      - Treasury Department, 1945
      - United States Tariff Commission, 1944-1945
      - War Department
        - Adjutant General's Office
          - Jacobs, Donald, 1944-1945
          - Miscellany, 1945, (7 folders)
            - A-F, (2 folders)
            - G-Z, (5 folders) (Box 26)
          - Stoll, Richard W., 1944-1945
        - Alaska and West Coast trip
          - Miscellany, 1942-1943, (2 folders)
          - Soldiers' letters, 1942-1943, (4 folders)
        - Army Air Forces, 1945
        - Army Service Forces (Box 27)
          - German prisoners of war, 1945
          - Miscellany, 1945
          - Office of the Judge Advocate General, court-martial of James M. Thompson, 1945
          - Office of the Provost Marshal General, 1945
        - Miscellany, 1945
        - Office of Dependency Benefits, 1944-1945
        - Office of the Chief of Engineers, 1945
    - General
      - Abney, Arvel, 1944-1945
      - American Automobile Association, 1945
      - American Bar Association, 1945
      - American Economic Foundation, 1943-1945
      - American Legion, 1941-1945
      - American Magazine, 1942-1945, undated
      - American Red Cross, 1941-1944
      - Andrews, Fletcher, 1945
      - Antioch College, Yellow Springs, Ohio, 1943-1945
      - Apartment House Owners Association, Cleveland, Ohio, 1941-1945
      - Archer, V. J., 1942-1945
      - “Ab-Am” miscellaneous, 1942-1945, (3 folders)
      - “An-Ax” miscellaneous, 1943-1945, (2 folders) (Box 28)
      - Baily, Harold J., 1941-1945
      - Ball, Joseph H., 1943-1944
      - Basore, A. K., 1942-1945
      - Bowling Green State University, Bowling Green, Ohio, 1943-1945
      - Brainard, Henry S., 1942-1945
      - Bridges, Styles, 1943-1945
      - Brown, Katherine K., 1941-1945
      - Byrd, Harry Flood (1887-1966), 1941-1945
      - “Ba-Br” miscellaneous, 1944-1945, (8 folders)
      - “Bu” miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 29)
      - Caldecott, Ernest, 1944-1945
      - Campbell, Willard D., 1944-1945
      - Capitol Page School, Washington, D.C., 1942-1945, (2 folders)
      - Children's Museum of Washington, D.C., 1944-1945
      - Citizens League of Cleveland, Ohio, 1941-1945
      - Clapp, Paul S., 1945